[Music]
this film is part of rebel wisdoms
series the science and psychology of
polarization scientist Steven Porges
came up with a revolutionary theory that
links together psychology neuroscience
and evolutionary biology it was called
polyvagal and focused on the vagus the
longest nerve in the body that links
together all the major organs and also
connected to the face and voice for the
first time there was a theory that
explained how our own body and mind are
intimately connected to our facial
expressions voice and social engagement
system and therefore to others how the
vagus nerve moderate sixes of trust and
safety how we're curious and open to new
information and experiences and how if
we're not feeling safe then we fall into
defensiveness we start to see everything
unfamiliar as a threat and are unable to
take in new information so Steven thank
you very much for making the time for
this interview you know David thank you
very much for inviting me
so in this interview I'm really
interested to talk about how your theory
polyvagal theory applies to the
polarization that we're seeing around us
could do you outline your what what is
polyvagal theory and how does it apply
to the subject polyvagal theory from the
perspective our dialogue is a
neurobiological theory that enables us
to understand why and how humans need to
connect with each other and if we don't
connect with each other what are the
consequences both to our body meaning
our physiology and our health but also
to our mental health it's basically a
theory that explains brain body
relationships and how we can manipulate
our mental perspective by shifts in our
body and how our mental perspective can
change our body and vice versa it's a
it's a direction of it's a model that
has by directionality between brain and
body and it enables us to use as
creative science of how social behavior
supports health and how being healthy
enables us to be more
just to talk about what polyvagal theory
actually means in in practice just like
to break that down in terms of the vagus
nerve and in a very simple way how do we
orient ourselves and how does how does
polyvagal theory illustrate that
orienting process polyvagal theory has
several features or we'll go through a
few of them the important the first
important one is that it gives us a way
of organizing our own poverty reactions
it really emphasizes that the neural
which really means the brain regulation
of the autonomic nervous system the
neural system that regulates the the
organs within our body followed an
evolutionary tradition trajectory so we
had a very primitive autonomic system
that really was about maintaining
metabolic resources so it was very much
oriented in if there was enough oxygen
of food it just kind of shut us down
then with evolution from these ancient
vertebrates that had only one a very
ancient old vagal circuit and that old
vagal circuit was unmyelinated and
myelination is really the fatty
substance that coats a nerve and if it's
myelinated it could actually convey
these signals more efficiently and more
specifically but in the very ancient
vertebrates they only have his older
dorsal vagal system but we still have it
it's the primary system that still goes
to our gut and the major defense
response of that the autonomic nervous
system for these ancient vertebrates was
basically shutting down immobilizing
death feigning through evolution a
sympathetic nervous system came onboard
and that one was a spinal sympathetics
that came on with the bony fish and you
can see them moving and even stopping so
now you have an autonomic pounce
I hope mobilization through the
sympathetic nervous system and
immobilization at old Vegas and
then what you have with mumbles and this
is the interesting part of polyvagal
theories
something strange is something a
miraculously occurs with the transition
from the ancient as stink extinct
reptiles to mammals and that is you have
a newer vagal circuit that's bile in it
that helps calm or coordinate these the
older veil circuit to support
homeostasis and to enable some things to
work without giving you into fight or
flight but the other miraculous part is
that the area of the brain that
regulates that pathway the vagus is not
the same that regulates the old Vegas
going to the gut it's linked to the
nerves in the area of the brainstem is
linked to the part that regulates the
nerves they regulate your face the
muscles of your face and head it
regulates your social engagement system
your ingest of system the way you touch
and connect with the world so it's
really this kind of remarkable
transition where our heart became
connected in a normal way to the the
nerves that regulate our voice the
intonation of our voice our facial
expressions and even our ability to
extract information by listening so
there are muscles in our middle ear to
our facial expressivity and the
intonation of our voice so now we
project of our heart in our voice and
people know that intuitively they
respond that way we project our feelings
in our face so these become the
important parts of how we make
connections with others but the
bidirectionality so that we're in a
sense of a person is in a physiological
destabilized way their voice is very
different and we often in for a good
therapist or great human beings and good
parents or good teachers we know that
and we calm them and how do we calm them
it's not the words that are powerful
it's how we use the words it's the
intonation of her voice
so polyvagal theory emphasizes these
evolutionary stages but also emphasizes
that under challenge under demands at
the illness or threat our autonomic
nervous system shifts state it moves
from this social engagement safe stage
where we are connected with others it
moves to defensive States and we have
two defensive States and this is really
one of the important points of polyvagal
theory
prior to polyvagal theory most people
thought we only had one defensive state
then that was a stress or a fight/flight
sympathetic state and even people who
had been traumatized who can be
immobilized by the trauma their
therapist would say oh you must have
been frightened you must have been
mobilizing but they kept on looking for
this sympathetic response and the client
said that's not how it experienced it
that's because when we experienced a
life threat for some of us not all of us
our body goes into this very very
ancient immobilization response we're
very much like a mouse and the jaws of a
cat with a mouse will just literally
pass out and lose all muscle tone and
many people who have survived trauma
their body has gone into that state and
they've not found a voice or had
difficulty finding a voice to explain
the mechanisms of it so frequently under
demands our bodies don't support fight
or flight and in our culture when that
doesn't it when we don't have that
resource the people often blame for not
fighting or not fleeing and so by
explaining this was probably vagal
theory it provides a validation for many
people's experiences and how does that
apply to - polarization and - connection
let's start with this whole notion you
have polarization in part because there
is some type of threat that people
perceive or their bodies respond
so let's now deal with this notion of
threat from a polyvagal perspective poly
vehicle theory doesn't like to use words
like perception because perception is
very cognitive term polyvagal theory
uses a term called neuro
which is the nervous systems decision or
evaluation of risk in the environment so
if the your honor if your nervous system
detects risk of danger you shift
physiological state to be more
sympathetically innovative which gives
you the power and strength to run or
define if you react as if there is no
way you can get out like your enclosed
in a small area or your physically much
smaller or your body might now move into
this life threat shutting down response
both of those are autonomic responses
and our body has this capacity to go to
those stages in an adaptive strategy to
save our lives so it's not like oh I
gave up so I just shut down now I'm
really angry that I gave up your body is
making that decision and once you
understand that these are more on a
neural reflux level then aspects of
shame and blame change well let's move
back to this notion of perceived threat
or a no reception of threat if we have a
neuro ception of threat our nervous
system loses its capacity to be socially
engaged with others so we start to see
others with a bias of threat threatening
us and then this goes into the next
level the issue of the world that were
in now which is a very polarized world
that we have confused what it means to
be safe and that's part of where the
polarization occurs the polarization
starts when people think that I can be
safe if I remove threat and I see us
threatening you're not coming into my
country you're not coming into my town
you're not marrying my daughter you know
all these features are basically we're
going to remove the threat but that's
not enough or bodies want more that will
never make an individual or community or
society feel safe safety comes when the
features of safety are being presented
to them on a day to day basis the
ability of people engaging them smiling
at them with positive gestures the
intonation z' of voices that are
reassuring
and witnessing those make people feel
safe so it's not really the politics we
have to also talk about educational
systems let's talk about medical care
how often do do the educators how often
are they instructed or their medical
providers instructed that the way they
look at the students or their patients
the way they use their voice is as
important as everything else they do
they're not does not part the curriculum
and that's what I think polyvagal theory
could bring to medical treatments and
education is the understanding that if
you want people to get better if you
want people to learn they have to feel
safe in the context in which you're
delivering your services and how does
this theory or theoretical framework
apply to say conflict and mediation well
it defines conflict doesn't in terms of
that we've conflict so people feel that
there is a threat or their bodies feel
as a threat to have remediation you have
to provide sufficient views of safety so
that you now get into a dialogue now a
dialogue by nature or being the word
implies some reciprocity in the
interaction and when you do rest we have
reciprocity in the action you have a
listening component as well as
expressive component so you have a
witnessing component so it part of I
think the major issue of conflict is
that people don't listen to each other
so they're not witnessing and if people
don't listen to you when you strike a
chalk express something or let's say
you're even a child and you're not being
listened to what happens to your
physiological state will you become very
uncomfortable you'll become frustrated
and as you get older with those same
feelings you become angry and
belligerent and so we have to understand
that being listened to being witnessed
not necessarily being agreed with but
being witnessed and appreciated for what
you were saying is really part of our
birthright it's something that we scream
to do AB and polarization is occurs when
people who aren't listened to there now
witnessed and they feel marginalized and
where do you see that happening at the
moment in in culture I see it happening
slowly I see to me for my own experience
the shock has been the interest in my
own ideas in the ideas of the polyvagal
theory and the fact that people in
education people in medicine and even
people in philosophy became interested
in so it's not really the psychologists
or the neuroscientists that people who
are living their lives said ah this is
an interesting theory it explains my
experiences or what I would say to them
it provides them with a validation of
their own intuitions and I think what
that is saying to me is that as we
understand the neurobiology of what it
is to be a human being when that becomes
our guide then culture and life becomes
better I I put on one of my slides a
couple of days ago at a kind of
modification at what DuPont the chemical
company used to say used to advertise
better living through chemistry that was
their their slogan and what I was saying
was we may be better living through
understanding neurobiology that are
living through neurobiology and what
polyvagal theory is saying that are
living through in your biology so rather
than always thinking that our behaviors
are all based upon intentionality that
we have a a more sophisticated
understanding that we have a role the
role is to support our own biology and
that neurobiology is supported for being
a human in terms of coagulation or
social interactions what it teaches us
is that to be healthy we have to do lots
of interactions not all the time but we
have to have opportunities and what that
means is that we used to be called we
like to call play play as an oral
exercise social communication with each
other is a neural exercise and they have
certain principles one there's
synchronous in real time two
and the others they have reciprocity and
the world whirring with social media and
texting and all these other ways of
communicating has ruined the synchronous
and often the reciprocal aspects of it
and our nervous system gets retuned by
lack of via the helpful exercises so as
people are listening I hope that the
educational model starts to shift so
that we start providing more
opportunities for children earlier ages
to have neural exercises of these
systems because when those systems of
neural regulation start becoming more
say more tuned more powerful more
efficient we have better behavioral
state regulation and behavioral state
regulation is really the basis upon
which we can negotiate or talk to others
and the basis upon which we can learn so
we can't sit in a classroom unless we
can regulate our state and we are
starting to find out really that lots of
disorders including addictive behaviors
which are massive in our culture are
really disorders of state regulation so
polyvagal theory provides a different
perspective for many of the attributes
of mental illness and mental health and
you just touched on it a little bit but
social media and if if polyvagal theory
is all about the necessity for
face-to-face contact and for regulating
ourselves in connection with other
people what does social media do to that
when we're basically communicating
through a screen and we're well it's an
interesting question because for those
of us who initially our early part of
our lives was really solely face to face
even the telephone wasn't that bad
because we could tell by intonation of
voice I have found that Skype is better
than just talking so and I have become
more comfortable with interviews even on
skype resume so these types of social
media technologies are infiltrating our
life I don't think they replace the
one-to-one interaction
I often like to say that we don't have
to have these one-to-one interactions
all the time but we need to have some of
it so if we have a good nervous system
of our nervous system has been well
developed that's a good parenting good
friends good social interactions it
gives us the resilience to then go off
and do things on our own to be bolder to
be more creative and not to need
constant coagulation so there's almost a
paradox the more opportunities you have
as you develop the more resilient you be
you are I should grow up and the more
bold and you can do things but is there
a problem with social media and the sort
of the low bandwidth we're not face to
face much of the time it's very do you
think it adds to the kind of division or
isolation that we're experiencing I
think it adds to a misunderstanding of
queues where people are misunderstanding
what people are saying and they may be
listening more to the words and less to
the facial expressivity and the
intonation I think they're false cues
coming out there and but I have children
and they are adults now and they would
argue with me that social media plays a
positive role in their lives and they
have friendships that are maintained
because of social media and they use it
in a different way and then I would use
it I'm not comfortable with using it I
don't use Twitter and it's just down my
world I use email a lot and I do text
occasionally but I think it is an hour
bandwidth and it's it could be useful if
we have relationships already so
maintaining them but I think where my
kids are using it it's really
maintaining relationships with the
individuals they had worked with before
or gone to school with before so they
already have friendship relationships so
it's keeping them together
I feel that the act of looking at a
smartphone or looking at something
actually a small screen actually forces
certain physiological shifts like up for
our face gets really good contorted as
we attend to it that this is not a
comforting physiological state
I think larger screens larger monitors
are easier on our physiology and I think
our facial expressions reflect that so
if you look if you do Skype or something
on a large monitor people's faces look
reasonably normal if you start looking
down at this little thing you're you're
actually struggling and your body shifts
state one of the big light bulb moments
for me when I was thinking about
polyvagal theory and how it applies to
cultural and political conversation was
when one of my teachers talked about
curiosity and how curiosity was a key
value and how its moderated how
polyvagal theory can influence the
understanding what curiosity means
because when we're having a conversation
with someone when we're curious there's
a potential for kind of new information
and there's a potential to contain to
our minds when we stop being curious
then I kind of closed off and we're not
available for a generative conversation
so their important point you're bringing
up and let's start with this whole issue
of availability or being available I've
been playing with this whole issue of
vulnerability versus availability and
what we find out in certain cultural
environments if we feel that we're
concerned about evaluated we're
concerned about our own vulnerability
and when we're in that state of
vulnerability we're not truly available
and we're not expansive in the way we
think were aggressive and we try to hold
on to our existing beliefs or knowledge
but when we feel safe in the environment
and we're accessible for a true
interaction the interaction is much well
more welcoming for ideas that are
divergent even with our own so we listen
we witness who may not necessarily agree
but we learn so curiosity is one of the
bonus points or bonus objects are bonus
values of having a physiological state
that is welcoming if you are a defensive
person if your state of concern and you
feel that your role is to reject because
that gives you a power then you'll never
be curious you know I I speak from a
history of being an academic and
academics know their power and their
power is not necessarily in being
curious their power is being skeptical
and the skeptic is very easy to be a
skeptic you just say no prove it to me
I don't understand it now that's not a
very interesting life the interesting
life is to learn from whatever you can
tell me maybe I'll learn something maybe
it'll shift my views but I have to be
welcoming for that I have to be in a
state that I feel that I'm not gonna be
hurt my body has to feel it's not going
to be hurt not really my cognitions so
this curiosity is really a almost a
litmus test of our physiological state
can we go somewhere that we've never
gone before are we secure enough to take
ideas that may undermine the ideas that
we spent decades of learning and
publishing papers on so curiosity is a
wonderful projective test I'd be
interested if you could just tie that
curiosity to polyvagal theory well for
me
curiosity cannot coexist when we're in a
physiological state of defense and what
that means physiologically is that
curiosity comes out of what I was
calling the social engagement system
which has this newer myelinated vagus
when you're in the physiological state
that supports the neural regulation the
face and the voice in the veil control
the heart it basically dampens or
Taine's our reactivity so we can react
but it's gonna be contained we're not
going to get violent we're not going to
throw things at each other so you may
challenge me I may feel a little bit
uncomfortable but my social engagement
system will make sure that my physiology
will not go out of a certain range don't
be able to maintain this social
interaction and we'll build on our ideas
so the the ability to listen and to be
curious is really based on being able to
regulate your physiology so that when
you're challenged you don't go ballistic
so I guess the 64 million dollar
question is how do we control our
physiology how do we have is it easy to
sense when we're getting into one frame
rather than the other and how do we how
do we shift now I see I think it's it's
really it's all what I think both of
your questions are on some level they're
very profound and important but not over
the trivial because yes people know when
they're losing it you know they and they
projected to others their faces change
they lose their effect and gets a flat
face the voices change we need to be
school to be able to understand this and
detect this and to realize that we might
have crossed into an area that triggers
a response we need to not really
understand the history of the person
we're talking to but we need to respect
that person so we may have a little
compassion and a little bit of ability
to witness but that should be part of
our curriculum as being human beings so
yes we can see this happening yes are
when our body shift state our tolerance
of sit still and to interact with other
decreases now the real point that I
think your ask is if that happens to be
or happens to you what can I do I'm
losing my physiological statement in
reality I don't want to get up I don't
want to fight I don't want to run I want
to maintain the relationship especially
if it's important for your career
your life and the answer is there
they're really relatively efficient ways
of rapidly changing your physiological
state bringing it back on board and the
most powerful one or of easy most easy
access to one is through breathing and
breathing is powerful because if we
extend the duration of our exhalations
meaning exhale slowly the vagal effect
on our sympathetic nervous system is
powerful it basically down regulates our
sympathetics so it starts to dampen our
defenses so when people say take breathe
slowly they didn't really mean that they
meant they could be breath and exhale
slowly because when you exhale slowly
there's a neuro physiological effect
that's occurring the vagal brake just
like a break down the car is now going
down on your sympathetic nervous system
down regulating those defenses and
calming you down so slow exhalations
what's interesting is that you can even
have a dialogue and use that so if
people extend the duration of their
phrases they're extending the duration
of the exhalation and you can see this
inserting dialogues when people take
breaths after each word and you probably
have seen people like that and what
they're doing is shifting their
physiological state to if they may
support anxiety but it also can support
aggression and the simplest things just
extend the number words you're saying
before you take a breath it seems when
we look out there's a ever-growing
polarization and there's an ever-growing
kind of spiral of polarization what do
you think when you see that and what
what does your work have to illustrate
or what do you think is the key thing to
understand from your work to illustrate
that well what's okay when you see the
polarization and you see it every day is
that the television not the first thing
that comes to mind is why would people
behave that way why would they be so
hurtful to others don't they have a
degree of compassion
don't they feel the pains of others and
the answers maybe they don't and the
reason maybe they don't is maybe they've
had traumatized series developmental
histories as well and that they're
really reenacting the trauma that has
happened to them I think this is really
a real tragedy in life because many of
the people who are this aggressive to
others hateful to others their lives
have been really not they have not been
lives of co-regulation and love and
caring of others
they've been lives of just trying to
survive and often using the wrong
metaphor the metaphor for survival is do
I have more stuff do I have more money
doing more land and that missed the real
issue is do I feel comfort but comforted
by being around other people do I like
people do I like my kids do I feel
excited about positive things not about
just getting more money or more things
so it's a real issue of for me when I
see this I feel that with great
compassion about but there are now
basically people who are I don't even
like to use word perpetrators I see this
and I look at that and I say this is so
sad
their lives are so sad but then I go to
the other one which is much more
pragmatic I can have the compassion for
them but I can't justify the amount of
people the number of people that they're
hurting the impact on the lives of
others and that really bothers me a lot
so you can say I can understand that I
have compassion for you for you're doing
or why you're doing it but I have a lot
of trouble because you're hurting people
and how can you hurt people and I think
I hope more and more people will have an
understanding of this I think the power
of those who do that who marginalize who
bully who who isolate people to whom
leave them treat them poorly to gain
power over them I just hope that more
more people understand that literally
the vulnerability of those people and
why they're doing that and not so in
politics we were talking a lot of this
there's always this pragmatic I can live
with that if I get what I want and I
think people have to just get beyond
that they have to say I'll never get
enough of you there I'll never get what
I need in a culture it's not ok with me
if you're hurting people it's just not
right so we have to have some different
levels of what Michael absolutes so we
started off our dialogue about the
biological imperative to survive was to
connect with others and polarization is
a violation of that biological
imperative and we have to literally draw
a line in that line in the ground is if
you start doing things that hurt people
it by it violates the imperative of what
we came what we evolve to be on this
planet we are connected species and if
we don't appreciate that we are in a
sense injuring the species and we have
to take on a responsibility the bottom
line is I think there are gonna be more
and more people having this
understanding because now you have with
polyvagal theory and neurobiology that
supports the philosophy LOF achill and
for many people even a spiritual
religious view so you have a convergence
of different orientations all ending up
in the same point and this is polarizing
people treating them as if they're not
human marginalizing them isolating and
bullying them is not how humans need or
have to our cessation it's not really
need or should if they keep doing that
they can't be humans it's almost like
you violate what it is to be a human so
do you say it as an existential threat
no I know I don't see it as an
existential threat because I see it as
something that will dissipate because I
don't think it's sustainable the main
point of this of the argument that it's
a violation of
of our biological imperative is that
it's transitory and can't be sustained
because being human is very powerful and
this work comes originally from trauma
understanding of trauma
why does it apply more widely is it
because we're all in a state of sort of
low-level trauma or is it well what's
interesting is my work didn't started
try I'm one of the few people in the
trunk world of trauma the world of
trauma therapy or trauma theory that
didn't come from initially from trauma I
came from my laboratory science and my
laboratory science led me into a model
and that model was polyvagal theory is a
model of the evolution of the autonomic
nervous system but it was also a model
that showed that under challenges the
autonomic nervous system shifted States
to more primitive and primitive states
of survival and so that is how it got
picked up by the trauma world because
people experienced severe trauma or
locked in these more defensive states
and then polyvagal theory started to
provide insights now you can move people
out of those states and it says
rehabilitate them to a more typical
neural regulation and with that more
typical social and emotional behavior so
because it was a general model of how
the million autonomic nervous system
works under challenge
it has great generalizability so it has
a generalizability not merely in the
world of trauma but has a generalized
ability in the world of education the
world of medicine and what I like to see
moving into is actually a world of
social politics or social justice is
really what we're talking about because
it's providing a different type of
manual of what it is to be a human being
so it's not a manual that's based upon
you know certain principles of that our
moral principles it's on principles of
what our body needs based upon our
evolutionary history and when those
principles kind of line up with moral
principles it's a beautiful story it
says
our bodies need to correctly we need to
feel safe with others we need to be safe
in the arms of selective people not
everyone we need time together where we
feel safe and we can and this will help
us grow and digest and will help us
learn it will help us solve problems and
be creative it will help us people and
will enable us to be curious and what
are the key things that you think people
need to know about that your work sheds
a light on I think the the major point
they need to know is that when you shift
physiological state it shifts your bias
of how you see the world so if you move
into a physiological state that is more
defensive you see the world much more
negatively and if you see the if you
shift into a physiological state as well
coagulate with other people you see the
world in a much more positive optimistic
perspective I think as people understand
that they'll start understanding the
relative import the relative way we see
the world is so physiologically
dependent that we'll go back to that
statement better living through
neurobiology we would want a life in
which we saw the world in a more
positive way and then we had a more
positive view of our purpose in life a
more positive view of learning and
curiosity and a greater acceptance of
other of witnessing others and enabling
people to be different than whom we are
Steven thank you very much no you're
welcome
rebel wisdom is a new sense making
platform bringing together the most
rebellious and inspiring thinkers from
around the world if you're enjoying our
content then you can help us make more
by becoming a subscriber which will give
you access to a load of exclusive films
also you can then join our group zoom
calls to discuss the ideas in the films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews we're also
looking for talented people to help us
out with editing graphics music that
kind of thing and if you're a regular
viewer you'll know we talk a lot about
the value of embodying or actually
living out the ideas that we talk about
so that's why we run regular events in
London check out the links on the
website for more and hope to see you
soon